Guide to the Start Furniture Collection, 1925-2021 MS 897
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Star Furniture Collection
1925-2021
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wolff Toomin, Shirley
MS 897
.75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
This collection is made up of two boxes containing photographs, news clippings, memorabilia, financial documents, and event programs from Star Furniture, and an oral history conducted with Shirley Wolff Toomim and Ellen Toomim Robinson spanning the years 1925-2021.
Scope and Contents
An oral history, photographs, news clippings, memorabillia, financial documents, and event programs from Star Furniture, a Texas furniture retailer which began as a small, family-owned Jewish business in 1912. Many materials are dedicated to Star Furniture staff life and social events. This collection has a number of annual financial documents for the years 1925-1932. Of particular interest is an official, signed copy of the inagural prayer for President Lyndon B. Johnson given by Rabbi Hyman J. Schachtel on January 20, 1965.
Biographical / Historical
Star Furniture was founded in Houston, TX in 1912 by three men with "only a horse and wagon to their name." In 1924, a Russian-Jewish immigrant named Boris Wolff purchased one-quarter interest in the furniture store, gradually gained ownership and began to pilot day-to-day operations. By 1950, Star Furniture had six locations, and Boris decided to pass ownership of the company over to his children, Melvyn Wolff and Shirley Wolff Toomim. In 1997, Star Furniture was sold to the multinational conglomerate Berkshire Hathaway, owned by Warren Buffett. Today, it is the longest running furniture store in the state of Texas.
Source: starfurniture.com
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research without restriction. Stored on-site at the Woodson Research Center.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged alphabetically as follows:
Series I: General Series II: Scrapbooks Series III: Oral History
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Shirley Wolff Toomin donated the papers in August of 2019.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Business
Document Types
business records
Places
Texas -- History, Local.
- Series I: General, 1925-1960; I
  - Annual Company Financial Records, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Inaugural Prayer For Lyndon B. Johnson Given by Rabbi Hyman J. Schachtel, 1965-01-20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christmas Party Photographs, 1970-12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Staff Signature Book, Gift to Melvyn and Shirly Wolff, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Scrapbooks, 1939-2001
  - Scrapbook #1, 1940-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook #2, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook #3, 1939-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook #3.5 (Loose Inside Scrapbook #3), 1969-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook #4, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook #5, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Oral History
  - Shirley Wolff Toomim and Ellen Toomim Robinson oral history interview and transcript, 2021